Mariusz Max Kolonko presents:
Discovering America.
When it begins
it's more popular here than the Super Bowl.
Just like in the football league,
fans have their favorites,
and gallery of stars.
That's Iditarod
the world's greatest sled dog race,
finished only by over 600 adventurers
for 35 years.
"Iditarod"
in Athabasca Indian language means:
"a place far away".
Today,
on Discovering America.
"A Place Far Away"
producer: Yvette Williams.
Local terms are descriptive,
and come from the Indian language.
"Alaska" means a land which is no island.
In fact, it's the largest America's state.
20% of U.S. territory,
looking mostly like this:
In summer temperature rises
up to 30 degrees,
In winter, drops to -50.
In March, wind blows on the streets,
among piles of snow reaching the rooftops.
The biggest town - Anchorage is less populated
than Poland's Bialystok,
but still it makes half of Alaska's population,
which is a bit more than 0,5 million people.
The tallest buildings
have about dozen of floors,
which is accordant to the law
and common sense.
the ground quakes here often.
These mountains keep growing
with the highest America's peak Mt. McKinley.
In the mountains' shadow rest
what's left after 7 on Richter scale.
People won't come back here.
Nearby you can hear death,
and the sound it makes:
It's snow rubbing snow.
Falling into this water
means death.
That's the "Water Of Return".
The name was given by the Capt. Cook's crew,
who thought it was a river.
The ship turned around,
as they didn't find a river,
thus the name "Water Of Return".
The water is not moved by the river's current,
but the ocean's tide,
sometimes with 20 km/h speed,
raising the water level by 10 meters.
But under the snow, there's a life:
when the winter ends,
belugas will come-the white whales.
I'm on my way to Wasilla,
where the Huskies are waiting for me.
I'm going down one of America's most scenic drives.
Alaska has only 8 highways
well maintained all summer,
so you can use them in winter.
Road signs
serve as shooting targets.
Nobody like Feds here.
65% of Alaska is owned by the state.
These signs better be respected:
avalanches killed many tourists taking pictures.
My top dog is the white giant over here.
Karen is preparing dogs for the team.
There will be 10 dogs' sled
half of the standard number,
but still it's a powerful force.
How powerful, I'm about to find out.
- 18F below at my house this morning,
-What boots you got?
-These are military boots,
good for very low temperatures
New York shoe looks poor in comparison.
Diane is one of the veterans of Iditarod.
- I started in '84, it took 12 days.
and 15 hours to complete the race
- All this time I slept only 23 hours.
Not to fall asleep is the most difficult.
-You feel so tired, everything hurts
you just want to sleep.
The race goes nearly trough entire Alaska
over 1800 km on sideways.
It will take over week or 2,
to cover this distance,
depending on conditions.
Iditarod has historic roots:
22 January 1925,
a telegram came from Alaska to Washington:
In a small town Nome,
a diphtheria epidemic outbroke.
The one thing that could save the people
was the huskies and mushers,
who moved to Nome
the same way that the race goes today.
That's the dog which reached Nome as first,
carrying the vaccines.
Its monument stands today
in Central Park in New York.
Every race's participant has such an envelope
in memory of those events.
And also now, as then,
the race helps those in need.
This is Tim.
He's 14, and has only few months of life left.
Tim suffers from incurable
nervous system disease.
Make a Wish Foundation
paid for his participation
in occasional start in Iditarod.
Tim loves dogs. He had one
but it couldn't pull him anymore.
Tim's parents came here from Colorado.
They believe, that nature will help Tim
to at least forget about disease.
Now Diane with friends
is preparing a sled for Tim.
-What kind of breed is that?
-Any breed, that can run and pull
- That brown one has a lot of Greyhound the one here looks more like Husky,
- it depends on how tough they are
- Can they survive in low temperatures?
- Can you too?
Dogs know they'll run soon
and it's an event of a day.
Big fuss starts,
New York musher has no experience with dogs.
Huskies are very patience
and help in putting harnesses on.
Each dog is a cog in a well oiled machine.
Scooby will be in a pair with Swing.
Scooby may be ready, but the camera is done.
Saliva froze on the objective instantly.
10 dogs' team passes by like a locomotive.
Only in slow motion you can see the details.
Huskies are in fact 2 breeds
of Siberian Husky and Alaskan Malamute.
They can sense a danger like a weak lake's ice,
and lead the sled themselves.
Huskies are born to run,
when they slip their chain,
they won't go back when called.
A single Malamute can pull a car,
sled, even a truck.
After a while, they run steady, trotting.
They could run like this 30-50 km daily,
with the average speed of over 30 km/h.
Dogs are not the same
-the best are worth $15,000 each.
Vern Holter is a race's veteran.
He participated 23 times in it.
-We're gonna take 10 dogs
and have a 15 km warm-up.
- 90% of the route you'll spend here
as a musher.
- This is a break to slow down the team,
- dogs will press ahead,
no matter the weight on the sled.
- Sleds are traditionally hand-made
by the Athabasca Indians.
- You'll give commands to the dogs:- go left-ho, go right-geee
- On the crossroads you say: straight.
- They run without a command,but to stop them you say: woe
- At the same time you press the break,
and take an anchor.
- Only the anchor stuck into the snow
can stop the team for good.
-Do dogs listen to those commands?
-You hope they do.
First I need to visit changing room.
What works in NY, seems a toy here.
These are Mukluks,
Eskimos and Athabascans wear these.
They are light and have leather soles.
Vern promotes also American Army's boots:
these are the best for Alaska.
What's the difference between this
and what's in your hands?
This suit protects your legs
today it's -20.
You need several layers,
no fashion rules apply,
clothes must be to large:
free spaces will give me warming air.
2 layers on my head,
and an "astronaut suit".
It's an Eskimo's jacket:
no zip, it's not easy to put it on,
better to have someone to help.
That's not all,
I need 3 pairs of gloves
second one for warming my wrists.
And finally: 10X size.
- What you're wearing now is what I wear during Iditarod.- my personal parka
A flashlight is a must,
dogs love to run at night.
- Notebook allows for dog's health control
- Inspector wrote here:
Team looks good",
and drew a smile,
which means that team is really looking good
But that's not always the case.
At least few dogs dies on each race.
Half of teams won't reach the finish line.
It's all about the training.
- Keep your knees bent
and I'll be balancing the sled.
- Let's take the dogs.
Each team has specific composition,
like a hockey team.
Huskies are reliable,
but difficult and often competitive.
They can't wait to run,
one gives me a dog-friendship sing.
- Runners are replaceable and mostly plastic
- Different type of plastic is used for different kind of snow,
- Eskimos know about dozen of snow kinds.
- Race's rule no.1 is no help from the outside.
Each checkpoint controls the dogs.
- What does it mean when they are barking?
-They're just telling you, they're happy and want to run.
When I pick up the anchor,
the fuss ends.
I go trough Alaska now,
and I must say it's not easy.
These dogs are the hardiest breed
of huskies,
they can run pulling the sled all day,
70 - 100 km daily, 25 km/h.
For me, as a musher, it's not easy job,
as there are branches, twigs, trees,
I must stand with my knees bent,
and control the dogs.
Doing this for 5,8,10 hours a day,
it's no picnic, believe me.
There's no time for more training.
Only one day left to the race.
Competitors will start from these streets tomorrow.
The snow is brought from the nearby mountains.
There's a lot of it this year.
It will take them about 3 hours
to cover the streets.
That's the last restful night
for 84 mushers and their teams,
who run in this year's marathon.
The race's participants are in town:
all hotels are full.
Anchorage has its Super Bowl.
You may recognize competitors
by the dog trailers.
There are 10 dogs at each side
Dogs, as the racehorses,
get special treatment.
- We've been training since mid October t's our first race, we want to finish it.
Mushers are heroes of a day.
Start will be broadcasted live on TV.
Reporters are plugged in,
local papers print the starting lists.
-Who's winning?
-They're all are now, but we know the winner:
-Why?
- She's from our town
- it's her 7th race, 5th in the row,
she's got a great team,
she's no 35 in the paper.
Others, have their own types:
-What brings you here?
-The race!
-I like the way you say: "race"
We have 83 competitors on the list.
From which countries?
- Mostly Alaska, also Canada, Colorado,<Norway, Serbia.
- No Poland?
But there's a Polish element here:
on the sausage stand. $5 for one.
Alaska is a strange land:
white bears walk on the streets,
PETA would be very busy here,
is it wasn't afraid of the locals.
Various kinds and colors of furs,
remind of the Gold Rush in Klondike,
with a grizzly bear
blessing  a street fair with both paws.
Finally, competitors come out.
This street race is of ceremonial kind.
Popular Senator Lisa Murkowski
is cutting the ribbon.
Each of the mushers
paid several to about
dozen of thousands of dollars to be here.
I recognize Tim,
who celebrates thanks to Make a Wish Foundation.
He will cross the start line
with the race's veteran Jeff King
This is Dee Dee Jonrowe,
who many people believe in.
- I hope to win this year.
- What are the 3 most important things for you?
- Money.Would be good to win some.
Dee Dee is pro.
She has earned over $400,000 on the races so far.
Everybody's ready except for...
I don't ask,
but I know that Diane and Karen
don't have $30,000 from sponsors,
to join this madness.
The prices of participation
are up to $100,000:
in dog's food, transportation costs, assistants' help.
To join this race,
you need to finish different one,
at least 500 miles long.
That's why here are the best of the best,
and those, who sponsors believe in.
The prize is nearly $100,000
and as much again in advertising contracts.
First musher on the midway
will receive $4,000 in gold lumps.
And so the world's greatest sled dog race begins.
Only half of teams will make it to the end.
They will spend 2 weeks
in snow and even -50 degrees.
Sometimes, they'll sleep with dogs
to stay warm.
26 checkpoints will control the dogs' health.
Teams of even 20 dogs,
go in 2 minutes intervals.
Only the toughest half of them
will finish the race.
Running at night will help to save the time.
Dogs love low temperatures,
nap time is in the morning.
But when the wind blows from the front
dogs won't go.
Their survival instinct is stronger
than musher's persuasions.
Helicopters will take those,
who can't keep up the pace.
Nome, a small town lost at the end of the world
is 12 days from here,
in the fairy tale land far far away.
Jeff King was 5th.
He run 1853 km in 9 days, 15 hours and 5 minutes,
although wolfs ate the signs
before the finish line.
Dee Dee Jonrowe broke her arm
during the race, and backed out.
She beat the breasts cancer,
which she considers her biggest success.
Tim came back to Colorado.
His condition didn't improve.
He counted 8 kinds of snow
and 7 colors of life on Alaska.
He says, next year he'll start in Iditarod.
I believe he will.
Editor: Tim Newman
Segment Producer: Yvette Williams
Director: Mariusz Max Kolonko
Based on the book: "Discovering America"
Producer:
Today on "Discovering America" - Alaska.
Not just from the car's window,
but also from the dogs' sled,
that I will drive on "Discovering America".
Stay tuned tonight, if we get there,
everything's possible.
This hood is p....s me off,
I'm f....g tired of it!
Can anyone turn the heat on it this ....
Is this ice tea drinkable already or what?