[THUNDER]
[DRUMMING]
[WOMAN SPEAKING UNANGAM
TUNUU LANGUAGE]
- THE STORY THAT I'M GOING
TO SHARE RIGHT NOW IS A STORY
THAT BELONGS TO OUR PLACE AS
OPPOSED TO BELONGING TO ANY
ONE PERSON.
[SPEAKING UNANGAM TUNUU]
TRADITIONALLY, WHEN WE HAVE
A STORY OF THIS NATURE,
IT DOESN'T BEGIN WITH
"ONCE UPON A TIME."
IT BEGINS WITH THE PHRASE
"TANAM AWAA," AND "TANAM AWAA"
MEANS "OUR COUNTRY'S WORK."
[SPEAKING UNANGAM TUNUU]
THE FIRST TIME THAT OUR PEOPLE
HAD ANY INTERACTION WITH THIS
ISLAND CAME IN THE FORM OF
AN ALEUT HUNTER, AND HIS NAME
WAS IG,ADAGAX,.
IG,ADAGAX, WAS OUT IN HIS SINGLE
HATCHED IQYAX, ON HIS OWN WHEN
HE WAS SWEPT AWAY IN A STORM
AWAY FROM THE SHORELINES
OF THE ISLANDS OF HIS VILLAGE.
HE CAME FROM WHAT WE NOW CALL
THE ALEUTIAN CHAIN, ISLANDS
THAT STRETCH FROM ALASKA
TO RUSSIA ON THE EDGE
OF THE BERING SEA.
HE TRAVELED A LONG PERIOD OF
TIME ON HIS OWN, AND HE ENDED
UP ON THIS ISLAND.
HE CAME AND HE STAYED LONG
ENOUGH TO SEE HOW LIFE EXISTED
HERE, LONG ENOUGH TO SEE THAT
THERE WERE FUR SEALS HERE,
THAT THERE WERE SEA OTTERS
HERE, THAT THERE WERE MANY SEA
BIRDS HERE.
SO HE PROBABLY STAYED A
WHOLE YEAR, ONE WHOLE CYCLE.
IG,ADAGAX, TOLD THE STORY TO HIS
BROTHER, TO HIS SON, TO HIS
RELATIVES, AND HE SAID THAT
HE ALWAYS WANTED TO COME BACK.
IG,ADAGAX, WANTED TO COME BACK,
AND HE DID, THROUGH US,
BY US BEING HERE, AND BEING
THAT WE ARE A PEOPLE THAT LIVE
GENERATIONALLY, YOU CARRY ON
WHAT HAS BEEN PASSED DOWN FROM
PEOPLE BEFORE YOU.
WE HAD TO COME, IF NOT ONLY
TO FULFILL IG,ADAGAX,'S NEEDS,
BUT ALSO TO PROTECT
THE FUR SEAL.
WE HAVE HAD TO BE KEEPERS OF
THE SEALS AND MAKE SURE THAT
THEY CONTINUE TO LIVE HERE
BECAUSE IF THE FUR SEALS
AREN'T HERE, THEN WE
WON'T BE, EITHER.
- [CHATTER]
[HORN BLOWS]
- WHOO!
- [CHEERING]
- SO WHO ARE WE, THE
PEOPLE OF THE SEAL?
NOW WE'RE AMERICAN CITIZENS,
ALASKAN NATIVES.
- GO, GO, GO, GO!
- MANY OF US STILL BEAR OUR
RUSSIAN HERITAGE IN OUR NAMES,
LIKE MERCULIEF, ZACHAROF,
MELOVIDOV, BOURDUKOFSKY, AND MY
LAST NAME, LESTENKOF.
AND WE'RE ALEUTS, OR AS WE
CALL OURSELVES IN OUR OWN
LANGUAGE, UNANGAN, NATIVES
OF THE ALEUTIAN ISLANDS AND
OF A CULTURE THAT STRETCHES
BACK AT LEAST 9,000 YEARS.
WHO WE ARE WEAVES TOGETHER
AT LEAST 3 VERY
DIFFERENT TRADITIONS.
OURS IS A STORY OF SURVIVAL,
OF ADAPTATION, AND A CONSTANT
THREAT OF EXTINCTION.
WHAT'S HAPPENING ON THESE
REMOTE ISLANDS IS BEING
REPEATED ALL OVER THE WORLD.
NATIVE CULTURES AND NATIVE
SPECIES ARE FIGHTING TO KEEP
FROM DISAPPEARING.
MY NAME IS AQUILINA
DEBBIE LESTENKOF.
WHEN I WAS LITTLE, GROWING UP,
I JUST REMEMBER THAT ALL THE
ELDERS CALLED ME BY AQUILINA,
AND FOR THEM IT WAS RESPECTING
MY BAPTISM IN THE
ORTHODOX CHURCH.
DEBBIE MEANS BUMBLEBEE, SO MY
ALEUT NAME IS AANASNAADAX,,
AND AANASNAADAX, TRANSLATES
INTO ENGLISH AS BUMBLEBEE.
THIS IS SAINT PAUL ISLAND.
THIS IS WHERE I LIVE.
PRESENTLY WE HAVE ABOUT 450
PEOPLE RESIDING ON
SAINT PAUL ISLAND.
PEOPLE COME AND THEY SAY,
"OH, THAT'S IN THE MIDDLE
OF NOWHERE," BUT REALLY,
IT'S IN THE MIDDLE OF IT ALL.
SAINT PAUL ISLAND AND ITS
SISTER ISLAND SAINT GEORGE ARE
CALLED THE PRIBILOF ISLANDS.
THEY ARE 300 MILES WEST OF THE
MAINLAND OF ALASKA, 250 MILES
NORTH OF THE ALEUTIAN CHAIN,
AND WAY CLOSER TO RUSSIA THAN
TO ALASKA'S STATE
CAPITAL IN JUNEAU.
WE'RE DRIVING ON MAIN STREET,
WHAT WOULD BE CONSIDERED MAIN
STREET DOWNTOWN, AND IT'S
NOT WHAT IT WAS WHEN I
WAS YOUNGER.
WE SEE BUILDINGS
THAT ARE BOARDED UP.
WE HAVE A HISTORIC HOTEL
THAT IS NOW BOARDED UP AND NO
LONGER USED, AND WE HAVE WHAT
WAS AN OLD GOVERNMENT OFFICE
WHEN THE GOVERNMENT MANAGED
THE COMMERCIAL FUR SEAL
INDUSTRY, AND IT'S
ALL BOARDED UP.
FOR ALMOST 200 YEARS,
WE UNANGAN PEOPLE HAVE HAD OUR
LIVES RULED BY ONE THING: THE
COMMERCIAL HARVEST OF FUR
SEALS TO MAKE FUR COATS.
IT WAS AN INDUSTRY WORTH
MILLIONS AND MILLIONS
OF DOLLARS, BUT IT ALL CAME
TO A CRASHING HALT IN 1983.
THAT'S WHEN PRESSURE FROM
ANIMAL RIGHTS GROUPS LED THE
UNITED STATES GOVERNMENT TO
PUT AN END TO THE COMMERCIAL
HARVEST OF FUR SEALS.
WHAT WAS MEANT TO PROTECT THE
FUR SEALS INSTEAD LED TO
THE FUR SEALS BEING IGNORED.
[FUR SEALS GRUNTING]
SOMEONE ONCE SAID THAT
THE PRIBILOF ISLANDS ARE
A MICROCOSM.
THIS IS A PLACE WHERE WE CAN
LOOK AT HUMAN INTERACTIONS
WITH THE PLANET IN GENERAL.
WHERE ARE WE GOING TO GO NEXT?
I CO-DIRECT THE ECOSYSTEM
CONSERVATION OFFICE
FOR THE ALEUT COMMUNITY
OF SAINT PAUL ISLAND'S
TRIBAL GOVERNMENT.
IT IS OUR RESPONSIBILITY
TO ENSURE THAT NOT ONLY
THE ENVIRONMENT BUT ALL THE
SPECIES THAT HAVE PROVIDED
FOR OUR PEOPLE CONTINUE TO
EXIST IN ORDER THAT WE AND OUR
CULTURE CONTINUE TO EXIST.
[FUR SEALS GRUNTING]
MY FIRST MEMORIES OF THE FUR
SEALS ARE KIND OF LIKE YOUR
VERY BEST FRIEND.
YOU DON'T REMEMBER WHEN
YOUR FRIENDSHIP STARTED.
THE SOUNDS OF THE FUR SEALS
HAVE HAD TO BE EMBEDDED
IN MY MEMORY.
EVEN WHEN THEY LEAVE HERE IN
THE WINTER, THE SOUNDS ARE
STILL WITH ME.
[FUR SEALS GRUNTING]
WE CAN ONLY FATHOM HOW LONG
THESE ISLANDS HAVE BEEN HERE,
AND THE FUR SEALS, THEY'VE
BEEN HERE MANY, MANY YEARS
BEFORE HUMANS HAVE COME TO
THE PRIBILOF ISLANDS.
FUR SEALS ARE MIGRATORY.
THEY SPEND THE
WINTERS OUT AT SEA.
THEY DON'T COME BACK
ASHORE TILL LATE SPRING.
IN THE MIDDLE OF WINTER,
THE ROOKERIES ARE EMPTY.
YOU CAN WALK OUT AND YOU
CAN SMELL THEIR PRESENCE.
THEN BY MARCH, THE BULL
SEALS START TO COME.
THEY HANG AROUND
ON THE SHORES.
AND IN THE SUMMER, WE HAVE AN
INCREASE OF SOUNDS, OF SMELLS,
KIND OF LIKE TURNING
UP THE VOLUME.
[FUR SEALS BARKING LOUDLY]
NEVER A DULL MOMENT.
RIGHT NOW IT'S FALL.
THE CHILDREN ARE BACK AT
SCHOOL, AND THE FUR SEAL PUPS
ARE IN SWIMMING SCHOOL.
THEY DO HAVE TO LEARN TO SWIM.
THEY WEREN'T BORN KNOWING
HOW TO SWIM, OTHER THAN
HAVING FLIPPERS.
PEOPLE MAY THINK THAT IT IS
THE SAME, BUT IT IS DIFFERENT
EVERY YEAR.
IT'S NOT SOMETHING
YOU GROW TIRED OF.
IT IS SOMETHING THAT YOU
LOOK FORWARD TO AND KNOW THAT
YOU ARE HOME.
WHEN THEY COME HOME,
YOU'RE HOME, TOO.
BUT HOW DID THE HOME OF THE
FUR SEALS BECOME OUR HOME?
THESE WIND-SWEPT,
TREELESS ISLANDS, SEEMINGLY
UNINHABITABLE, SURROUNDED
BY THE COLD, ROUGH WATERS
OF THE BERING SEA.
THE TATTOO ON MY FACE TELLS
THE STORY ABOUT THE JOURNEY
OUR ANCESTORS
TOOK TO GET HERE.
THE CURVES REPRESENT FUR
SEALS, AND THE CIRCLES
REPRESENT THE 5 GENERATIONS OF
MY FAMILY THAT LIVED ON THESE
UNANGAN ISLANDS.
ALASKA IS HOME TO OVER 200
FEDERALLY RECOGNIZED TRIBES
SPEAKING 22 UNIQUE DIALECTS.
THE UNANGAN PEOPLE COME FROM
THE ALEUTIAN ISLANDS, AND WE
HAVE AT LEAST 3 DIALECTS.
THE FIRST OF MY UNANGAN
RELATIVES THAT SHOWS UP
IN THE WRITTEN RECORD
IS MY GREAT-GREAT-
GRANDMOTHER NEDEZHDA.
I KNOW THAT SHE WAS BORN ON
ATKA AND THAT SHE HAD LIVED
PART OF HER LIFE ON
BERING AND ATTU ISLANDS.
- UNANGAN CULTURE WAS SHAPED
BY A TREMENDOUS RANGE OF BOTH
CHALLENGES AS WELL AS
OPPORTUNITIES, AND RESPONDING
TO AN EXTRAORDINARILY
DYNAMIC ENVIRONMENT
OVER THE SPACE OF 9,000
YEARS LED UNANGAN PEOPLE
TO DEVELOP AN AMAZING ARRAY
OF TECHNOLOGICAL ADAPTATIONS,
INCLUDING, OF COURSE,
THE FAMOUS KAYAK, WHICH WAS
THE FASTEST VESSEL
IN THE WORLD.
I MEAN, THOSE THINGS
COULD DO 12 KNOTS.
BEAUTIFULLY ENGINEERED
TO RESPOND TO
THE MARINE ENVIRONMENT.
WEAPONRY SUPERBLY ADAPTED
FOR GETTING SEA MAMMALS.
A DIFFERENT STYLE OF POINT
WAS DESIGNED FOR EVERY TYPE
OF SEA MAMMAL.
GUTSKIN CLOTHING SEWED
TOGETHER WITH BONE NEEDLES
SO FINE THAT SOME OF THE
HOLES WERE BARELY AS BIG AS
A HUMAN HAIR.
A WATERPROOF STITCH WAS
DEVELOPED TO HOLD THESE
GUTSKIN GARMENTS TOGETHER.
SO AN AMAZING ARRAY OF
GADGETRY IS REFLECTED
IN THE ARCHAEOLOGICAL RECORD.
[MAN SINGING IN UNANGAM TUNUU]
- THAT KNOWLEDGE, PASSED
DOWN THROUGH THE GENERATIONS,
IS FAST DISAPPEARING.
TODAY ONLY A HANDFUL OF PEOPLE
KNOW HOW TO GET A MEAL FROM
A TIDE POOL.
VINCE TUTIAKOFF IS ONE OF THEM.
- WHERE WE'RE WALKING,
THOUSANDS OF YEARS AGO,
THE ALEUTS WERE OUT HERE
PICKING THEIR BREAKFAST
AND THEIR LUNCH.
GREEN KELP--THEY'D COLLECT
THAT TO COOK WITH THEIR FISH.
THEY'D FISH OFF THESE LITTLE
EDDIES IN HERE AND GET POGIES,
BLACK BASS, SEA EGGS,
BIDARKIES, BULLHEADS EVEN.
HUNTING IN THEIR LITTLE
BOATS ALONG THE EDGES
FOR SEAL, SEA LION.
- MM-HMM. SO, WHAT YOU'RE
SAYING IS WE'RE GOING TO
THE UNANGAN SUPERMARKET.
HA HA HA!
- UNAGAN SUPERMARKET.
YEAH, THAT'S IT.
WATCH WHERE YOU'RE WALKING.
DON'T STEP ON OUR
BREAKFAST OR LUNCH HERE.
[BOTH CHUCKLE]
RIGHT NOW THE SEA URCHINS
SHOULD START TO BE FILLING UP,
AND THEY'LL HAVE A LOT
OF EGGS IN THEM.
A LOT OF PROTEIN AND IRON.
AND THERE IT IS.
THERE ARE SOME
EGGS RIGHT THERE.
AND THEY'D SCOOP THEM OUT
JUST LIKE THAT AND
OF COURSE EAT THEM.
CARVE THIS GUY.
THIS IS A TONGUE HERE.
- IS THAT EDIBLE, TOO?
- YES. THAT'S THE BEST PART.
THAT'S GOOD EATING THERE.
IF IT WASN'T FOR THE RED TIDE,
WE'D HAVE A DINNER.
- YEAH.
- HERE'S THE GRASS THAT
ALEUTS FED TO THE RUSSIANS
WHEN THEY FIRST GOT HERE.
LOT OF THEM HAD SCURVY
OR SOME SORT OF SICKNESS.
THERE WAS NO DOCTORS HERE,
EITHER, YOU KNOW, FOR YEARS.
DIDN'T HAVE A CLINIC HERE.
- YEAH.
- GONNA CUT ONE OFF.
AND WHAT THEY DO IS CHOP IT UP
AND BOIL IT,
AND WHAT COMES OUT OF THE LEAVES
AND OUT OF THE VINES,
THEY DRINK IT.
IT'S LIKE A TEA.
TRY ONE OF THESE HERE.
THEY'RE--ONCE YOU CHEW ON THEM--
YOU'LL FIND IT VERY BITTER.
- IT'S KIND OF LIKE
IF YOU LEFT SOME SOAP
AND YOU TASTED IT,
THAT'S THE BITTER.
- YEAH.
SAVED A LOT OF RUSSIANS' LIVES,
AND MAYBE THEY SHOULDN'T HAVE.
OR THERE'D PROBABLY BE
MORE OF US AROUND TODAY.
[LAUGHTER]
- [MAN SINGING
IN UNANGAM TUNUU]
- ONE OF THOSE RUSSIANS SAVED
WAS MY GREAT-GREAT-GRANDFATHER
MIKHAIL LESTENKOF.
HE BEGINS THE RUSSIAN CHAPTER
OF MY FAMILY HISTORY.
MIKHAIL WAS BORN
DURING THE REIGN OF
CATHERINE THE GREAT,
AT A TIME WHEN
THE RUSSIAN EMPIRE
WAS GROWING RICHER
THROUGH THE FUR TRADE.
MIKHAIL WAS ONE OF HUNDREDS
OF YOUNG RUSSIAN MEN
CALLED PROMYSHLENNIKI.
THEY WERE TRAPPERS AND TRADERS
WHO WERE THE BACKBONE
OF THIS SOFT GOLD RUSH.
- THE FIRST RUSSIANS WHO CAME
TO ALASKA AND THE ALEUTIAN CHAIN
WERE MARINE MAMMAL HUNTERS,
AND MOSTLY WHAT ATTRACTED THEM
WAS THE SEA OTTER,
BECAUSE SEA OTTERS BROUGHT
EXCEEDINGLY HIGH PRICES.
SO THAT WAS WORTH THE RISKS.
- MIKHAIL TRAVELED OVER LAND
THOUSANDS OF MILES...
THEN HE SET SAIL
FOR BERING ISLAND,
WHERE HE FIRST ENCOUNTERED
THE UNANGAN.
- WHAT THE RUSSIANS FOUND
WERE 30,000 HIGHLY ORGANIZED,
SUPERBLY ADAPTED MARINE HUNTERS,
AND THEY WERE ABLE TO TAKE
ADVANTAGE OF THOSE
TECHNOLOGICAL SKILLS
AND THAT KNOW-HOW
TO FORM THE FOUNDATION
OF THEIR FUR TRADE EMPIRE.
- IN 1805, A RUSSIAN SHIP--
"CONSTANTINE"--
DROPPED MIKHAIL AND 11 OTHERS
ON BERING ISLAND.
FOR 7 YEARS, THEY HAD NO CONTACT
WITH THE OUTSIDE WORLD,
AND THEY SURVIVED ONLY BECAUSE
OF UNANGAN GENEROSITY.
MIKHAIL BECAME A MANAGER IN
THE RUSSIAN-AMERICAN COMPANY,
WHICH WAS THE MONOPOLY
THAT RAN THE FUR EMPIRE
IN THE ALEUTIANS,
AND HE ENDED UP
MARRYING NEDEZHDA.
- WHEN PEOPLE IN THE ALEUTIANS
CAME IN CONTACT WITH
THE RUSSIANS FOR THE FIRST TIME,
THEY WERE IRREVOCABLY
LINKED INTO THE WORLD ECONOMY.
MARKET FORCES
IN OTHER CONTINENTS
WOULD DIRECTLY
AFFECT THEIR LIVES
THROUGH THE RUSSIAN FUR TRADE
IN TERMS OF
THE AVAILABILITY AND TYPES
OF TRADE GOODS
THAT WERE ENTERING
THEIR MATERIAL CULTURE.
- SOME RUSSIANS, LIKE MY
GREAT-GREAT-GRANDFATHER MIKHAIL,
EMBRACED OUR PEOPLE'S WAYS,
BUT OTHERS, THEY JUST
SOUGHT ONLY TO CONQUER.
THE RUSSIANS, THEY BROUGHT
DISEASES THAT OUR PEOPLE
HAD NO IMMUNITY TO,
AND WHEN THE UNANGAN REVOLTED
AGAINST RUSSIAN RULE,
THEY WERE KILLED BY RUSSIAN
RIFLES AND SWORDS.
- AT THE POINT
OF RUSSIAN CONTACT,
WITH THE INUIT PEOPLE
IN THE MID-18th CENTURY,
THE ALEUTIAN ISLANDS WERE
FAR MORE DENSELY POPULATED
THAN THEY ARE TODAY.
WITHIN THE FIRST 80 YEARS OR SO
OF RUSSIAN OCCUPATION
OF THE ALEUTIANS,
THERE'S AN 80%
POPULATION DECLINE.
WE REMEMBER THE BLACK DEATH
IN THE 1340s
AS THIS DRAMATIC EVENT
WHICH REALLY SHAPED THE COURSE
OF WESTERN CIVILIZATION.
BUT WHAT ARE YOU
TALKING ABOUT THERE?
I MEAN, YOU'RE TALKING ABOUT
30%, 1/3, 1/4.
THIS IS 80%.
IT'S AN ARMAGEDDON.
- THIS SLAUGHTER OF
SO MANY OF MY PEOPLE
LEFT A VOID THAT STILL
HANGS OVER THESE ISLANDS.
THE SURVIVORS, THEY KEPT ALIVE
SOME TRADITIONAL WAYS,
BUT MORE AND MORE, THE RUSSIAN
CULTURE TOOK HOLD.
MY GREAT-GRANDFATHER INNOKENTY
WAS A FORCE
IN THAT TRANSFORMATION.
HE WAS BORN ON THE ISLAND OF
ATTU IN 1832,
AND AT SOME POINT, MID-LIFE,
HE MOVED TO THE ISLAND
OF UNALASKA
TO SERVE THE COMMUNITY THERE
AS A RUSSIAN ORTHODOX PRIEST.
[BIRDS SQUAWKING]
- IT'S AMAZING TO ME HOW THROUGH
THE RUSSIAN ORTHODOX CHURCHES,
WE STILL HAVE
THE PRESENCE OF RUSSIA.
AFTER ALL OF THESE YEARS.
- ABSOLUTELY.
- WE STILL HAVE IT.
SHARON SVARNY-LIVINGSTON
IS LIKE ME--
TRYING TO BALANCE THE RUSSIAN
ORTHODOX FAITH WE WERE RAISED IN
WITH THE TRADITIONAL
UNANGAN VALUES
THAT WE BOTH WANT TO PRESERVE.
- WHEN THE RUSSIANS FIRST CAME,
MODERN ARCHAEOLOGISTS SAY
THE POPULATION
WAS SOMEWHERE BETWEEN
20,000 AND 25,000.
THE FACT IS THAT WITHIN 40 YEARS
OF THE RUSSIANS COMING,
THE POPULATION WAS
CUT DOWN TO ABOUT 3,000,
PROBABLY EVEN LOWER.
UM, AND WHEN YOU THINK
ABOUT THOSE NUMBERS,
UNALASKA ISLAND ITSELF
HAD 3,000 PEOPLE ON IT
BEFORE RUSSIAN CONTACT.
WHO WENT FIRST?
THE CHIEFS, THE SHAMAN.
SO YOU LOST YOUR BASIS
FOR YOUR RELIGION.
MISSIONARIES WITH INTENT
COME TO A PLACE AND INCORPORATE
TRADITIONS AND CULTURES
INTO WHAT THEY'RE
TRYING TO BRING,
AND, YOU KNOW, RUSSIAN ORTHODOXY
IS EXTREMELY RITUALISTIC.
SHAMANISM WAS VERY RITUALISTIC.
YOU KNOW, THEY BELIEVED
IN A GREATER BEING,
BUT IT WAS MORE TIED
TO THE ENVIRONMENT.
AND I THINK THEY BROUGHT
THOSE THINGS INSIDE THE CHURCH
TO MAKE IT AN EASIER TRANSITION
FOR THE PEOPLE.
INSTEAD OF DOING IT OUTSIDE,
LET'S GO INSIDE AND DO IT.
OK. YOU'RE GONNA BUILD
A INDOOR SPACE FOR US? SURE.
- [SINGING IN CHURCH SLAVONIC]
- WHEN I LISTEN TO
THE YOUNG MEN SING HERE,
I ALWAYS THINK ABOUT THE RUSSIAN
FUR HUNTER SHIPS' CREWS
SINGING THE EVENING PRAYERS.
EVERY SHIP CARRIED ICONS,
AND ON EVERY SHIP,
THE CREW HELD SERVICES.
I BELIEVE IN THE POWER OF MUSIC.
ALEUTS ARE VERY MUSICAL PEOPLE,
AND I FIRMLY BELIEVE IN MY HEART
THAT IT WAS THE MUSIC OF
THE SERVICE THAT ATTRACTED THEM.
- [MAN RECITING
CHURCH SERVICE]
- I ALWAYS HAVE TO WONDER
IF PEOPLE WERE REBELLIOUS
WHEN RUSSIAN ORTHODOXY CAME.
I'M SURE THAT PROBABLY
SOME OF OUR PEOPLE SAID,
"WHAT ARE THEY DOING
WAVING THAT INCENSE AROUND?"
- I WAS MYSTIFIED
WHEN I FIRST CAME TO ALASKA
OVER 35 YEARS AGO--
WHY DO THE PEOPLE
IN THE ALEUTIAN CHAIN
SO FERVENTLY HOLD ON
TO THIS ALIEN FAITH
THAT HAD BEEN INTRODUCED TO THEM
FROM SIBERIA,
NAMELY, THE RUSSIAN
ORTHODOX CHURCH?
IF THIS IS THE RELIGION OF THEIR
ENEMIES AND THEIR OPPRESSORS,
WHY WASN'T IT ALL ABANDONED
AS SOON AS THE RUSSIANS
WERE GONE?
IT SEEMS THAT THERE WAS
A WAY IN WHICH
EASTERN CHRISTIANITY
RESONATED WITH
THE ANCIENT TRIBAL BELIEFS
OF THE UNANGAN
AND THE ALUTIIQ PEOPLES.
THE MISSIONARIES TOOK THE TIME
TO LISTEN TO THE STORIES,
ANALYZE THOSE STORIES,
AND BUILD ON THAT FOUNDATION.
THEY CAME TO UNDERSTAND IT
IN THEIR OWN LANGUAGE
AND ADAPT IT TO THEIR OWN LIVES
AS IT BECAME THE VERY CENTER OF
ALEUT CULTURAL IDENTITY
AND ALEUT LIFE.
- YOU ARE GIVEN BETTER TREATMENT
UNDER THE RUSSIAN RULES
BY JOINING THE ORTHODOX CHURCH.
IF YOU DID THAT, YOU WOULD BE
TREATED MUCH MORE CIVILLY,
SO A LOT OF PEOPLE DID.
AND WHEN THEY DID, THEY HAD TO
TAKE ON RUSSIAN NAMES
WHEN YOU'RE BAPTIZED
IN RUSSIAN ORTHODOX CHURCH.
THIS IS WHY MOST ALEUTS
HAVE RUSSIAN NAMES TODAY.
[CHURCH BELLS RINGING]
- ONCE WE GRAB ON TO SOMETHING,
WE DON'T WANT TO LET IT GO.
WE MAKE IT OURS.
- [MAN RECITING CHURCH SERVICE,
CHORAL RESPONSE]
- BUT I ALSO THINK THE CHURCH
PROTECTED THE PEOPLE.
NOT ONLY FROM THE RUSSIANS,
WHEN THEY WERE SO BRUTAL,
BUT THEY PROTECTED PEOPLE
DURING THE AMERICANIZATION.
LIKE DAD SAID,
YOU HAVE TO TAKE CARE
OF SOMETHING THAT
TOOK CARE OF YOU.
- THAT'S RIGHT.
- AND IT DID
TAKE CARE OF OUR PEOPLE
THROUGH TRIALS AND TRIBULATIONS,
THROUGH DIFFERENT POLITICAL ERAS
AND SOCIAL PRESSURES,
LANGUAGE CHANGES.
- [PEOPLE SINGING HYMNS]
- [MAN RECITING CHURCH SERVICE]
- BUT HE ALSO SAID,
"SOMETIMES I LONG FOR THE DAYS
WHEN MY PEOPLE RESPECTED
THE EARTH, SEA, AND SKY."
AND I COULD SEE
THAT HE WAS TRYING
TO HAVE THE BEST OF BOTH WORLDS.
- AMEN.
- RUSSIAN ORTHODOX PRIESTS
CAN MARRY.
MY GREAT-GRANDFATHER INNOKENTY
WAS MARRIED AND HAD CHILDREN,
AND HIS OLDEST SON DMITRI
WAS MY GRANDFATHER.
MY GRANDFATHER DMITRI LESTENKOF
WORKED HERE ON UNALASKA
IN THE EARLY 1880s FOR
THE ALASKA COMMERCIAL COMPANY.
AND THE ONLY THING THAT I CAN
FIND LEFT OF THAT COMPANY
IS THE A.C. VALUE CENTER, AS IN
ALASKA COMMERCIAL VALUE CENTER.
BOTH MY GREAT-GRANDFATHER
INNOKENTY
AND MY GRANDFATHER DMITRI HAD
UNANGAN BLOOD AND RUSSIAN BLOOD,
WHICH MADE THEM CREOLES.
- [SINGING IN RUSSIAN]
- THE CONCEPT OF CREOLE,
OR PEOPLE WHO ARE
OF MIXED SLAVIC
AND INDIGENOUS BACKGROUNDS,
GOES BACK HUNDREDS OF YEARS
BEFORE ALASKA WAS EVEN
DISCOVERED BY THE RUSSIANS.
THE RUSSIANS WHO CAME
WERE REALLY NOT
BLUE-EYED, BLOND-HAIRED
SLAVS FROM MOSCOW.
THEY WERE PRIMARILY
MEN THEMSELVES OF MIXED
RACIAL AND CULTURAL BACKGROUNDS.
AND EVENTUALLY,
THESE MEN SETTLED
WITH THE ALEUT PEOPLE,
THE UNANGAN PEOPLE
IN THE ALEUTIAN CHAIN.
THE CREOLES HAD AN ELEVATED
STATUS IN ALASKA.
THEY WERE THE MAINSTAY
OF THE COLONY.
THE COLONY COULD NOT HAVE
FUNCTIONED WITHOUT THEM.
THERE WASN'T AN ASSAULT
ON NATIVE LANGUAGE AND CULTURE,
PER SE,
BUT THERE WAS
THE FOCUS ON TRAINING,
ESPECIALLY THOSE
OF MIXED BACKGROUND,
TO READ AND WRITE
AS WELL AS SPEAK
IN AT LEAST 2 LANGUAGES,
AND THEN THERE WERE
CREOLES WHO SPOKE 3 AND 4.
THEY DIDN'T ABANDON THEIR
LANGUAGE AND THEIR CULTURE,
BUT THEY ADDED TO IT.
- THIS CREOLE CULTURE
WAS THROWN INTO TURMOIL
WHEN THE UNITED STATES
PURCHASED ALASKA IN 1867
FOR $7.2 MILLION.
THE AMERICANS WERE
SO KEEN ON REAPING
THE FINANCIAL REWARDS
OF THE FUR TRADE,
AND THEY WERE JUST AS ADAMANT
ON IMPOSING
AMERICAN LANGUAGE AND CUSTOMS.
- AT THE TIME THE AMERICANS
ARRIVED IN ALASKA IN 1867,
ALEUTS WERE CONSIDERED THE ELITE
NATIVE PEOPLE IN THE TERRITORY.
TO BE AN ALEUT WAS TO BE
SOMETHING SPECIAL.
PARTLY THAT WAS BECAUSE
ALEUTS HAD BECOME
A VERY EDUCATED PEOPLE.
THEY WERE LITERATE IN RUSSIAN,
LITERATE IN ALEUT.
THEY HAD BEEN
MANAGERS, STOREKEEPERS.
THEY HAD BEEN TEACHERS,
PRIESTS, DEACONS.
BUT WITH THE ARRIVAL
OF THE AMERICANS,
THEY WERE NO LONGER ELIGIBLE
FOR ANY OF THOSE POSITIONS.
THERE WAS A SENSE THAT
ALEUTS WERE INDIANS
AND THAT THEY WERE
SAVAGE INDIANS,
BECAUSE THE INDIAN WARS
WERE STILL GOING ON
IN THE LOWER 48.
IN ORDER FOR AN ALEUT TO BECOME
A FULL PARTICIPANT
IN THE AMERICAN SYSTEM,
HE OR SHE HAD TO
ESSENTIALLY ABANDON
THEIR TIES
WITH THE ALEUT PEOPLE.
- AFTER THE AMERICANS CAME,
THEY DISCOURAGED EVERYTHING
THAT WAS NATIVE.
THEY DISCOURAGED
EVERYTHING THAT WAS ALEUT
AND WANTED TO DO AWAY WITH IT.
ABSOLUTELY YOU WERE NOT ALLOWED
TO SPEAK ALEUT IN SCHOOL.
YOU WERE PUNISHED FOR THAT.
- THE FEDERAL MARSHALS
GOT INVOLVED.
THEY ARRESTED PARENTS.
THEY CLOSED SCHOOLS FORCIBLY.
THE UNANGAN WERE BASICALLY
A PERSECUTED MINORITY
IN THEIR OWN HOMELAND,
WHERE THEY WERE
THE VAST MAJORITY
OF THE POPULATION.
- MY PARENTS,
WHEN THEY WERE GROWING UP,
GOING TO GRADE SCHOOL,
THEY WERE PUNISHED
FOR SPEAKING OUR LANGUAGE...
SO THEY DIDN'T WANT US
TO BE PUNISHED.
MY PARENTS COULD SPEAK
TO EACH OTHER IN OUR LANGUAGE
AND NONE OF US WOULD UNDERSTAND.
IT WASN'T SPOKEN TO US.
SO THERE WERE 9 OF US
IN MY FAMILY, 9 SIBLINGS,
AND NONE OF US
PICKED UP THE LANGUAGE.
UNANGAM TUNUU, THE LANGUAGE,
WASN'T THE ONLY THING
SLOWLY DISAPPEARING FROM
THE ALEUTIANS ISLANDS.
BY THE LATE 1760s, SEA OTTERS
HAD BEEN BROUGHT
TO THE EDGE OF EXTINCTION
BY THE DEMANDS
OF THIS FUR TRADE.
THE HUNTERS NEEDED
A NEW SOURCE OF FUR,
AND THEY FOUND IT
IN THE NORTHERN FUR SEAL.
THE EASIEST WAY
TO CAPTURE THE FUR SEALS
WAS AT THEIR BREEDING GROUNDS.
IN 1786, A RUSSIAN NAVIGATOR,
GAVRIL PRIBYLOF,
FOLLOWED THE NORTHERN FUR SEALS
TO THEIR ROOKERIES
ON SAINT GEORGE ISLAND.
THE RUSSIANS BEGAN BRINGING
UNANGAN MEN
FROM THE ALEUTIAN CHAIN
TO HARVEST THE FIRST SEALS,
AND BY 1867,
WHEN THE AMERICANS TOOK OVER,
THERE WERE SIZABLE SETTLEMENTS
ON BOTH ISLANDS.
IN 1882, MY GREAT-GRANDFATHER
INNOKENTY
MOVED TO SAINT GEORGE ISLAND
TO SERVE AS THE PARISH PRIEST.
HE HAD TO PETITION
THE ALASKA COMMERCIAL COMPANY
FOR YEARS TO GET THEM TO ALLOW
HIS SON DMITRI
TO RELOCATE, AS WELL.
[GULLS SQUAWKING]
THIS IS THE VILLAGE
OF SAINT GEORGE.
THIS IS WHERE I WAS BORN...
AND RIGHT OVER HERE BEHIND ME
IS THE HOME OF MY GRANDMOTHER
AND GRANDFATHER,
MY MOM'S PARENTS, AND SO
FROM THE TIME I WAS BORN
TILL I WAS ABOUT 4 YEARS OLD,
I SPENT A LOT OF TIME
COMING OVER HERE
TO MY GRANDMOTHER'S HOUSE...
AND WHEN I COME HERE, I ALWAYS
STILL FEEL QUITE AT HOME,
EVEN IF IT'S BEEN A FEW DECADES
SINCE I'VE ACTUALLY SPENT
MORE THAN A FEW DAYS HERE.
WHEN YOU COME HERE
TO SAINT GEORGE,
EVERYTHING IS NESTLED
ALL TOGETHER,
THE VILLAGE WITH THE BIRD CLIFFS
AND THE FUR SEALS.
IT'S ALL JUST RIGHT HERE
AT THE DOORSTEP OF THE VILLAGE.
MY GREAT-GRANDFATHER,
REVEREND INNOKENTY LESTENKOF,
WAS THE FIRST LESTENKOF
ON THE PRIBILOF ISLANDS,
AND HE SERVED THE PARISH HERE
IN THE LATE 1800s,
AND HERE IS WHERE HE IS BURIED--
REVEREND INNOKENTY
MIKHAILOVICH LESTENKOV.
IN THE BELIEF OF UNANGAN PEOPLE,
OUR LIFE IS A VISIT.
WE DON'T HAVE A WORD FOR DEATH.
WE USE A WORD THAT ACTUALLY
TRANSLATES INTO ENGLISH
AS "DONE VISITING THIS LAND."
WHEN THE AMERICANS TOOK OVER
THE FUR INDUSTRY
ON SAINT PAUL
AND SAINT GEORGE ISLANDS,
THEY BEGAN KEEPING
METICULOUS RECORDS.
PART OF MY JOB AT THE TRIBAL
GOVERNMENT OF SAINT PAUL
IS TO LOOK AT
THESE OLD ARCHIVES,
SO MY COWORKER
SAMANTHA ZACHAROF AND I
HAVE SPENT MANY HOURS
PORING OVER THESE RECORDS.
OH, I DIDN'T KNOW
THIS WENT BACK THAT FAR.
BOTH SAINT PAUL
AND SAINT GEORGE ISLANDS
WERE RUN LIKE COMPANY TOWNS.
THE UNANGAN WORKERS
WERE WARDS OF THE STATE.
- WE BECAME IN A STATE OF
SERVITUDE TO THE U.S. GOVERNMENT
AS THE ONLY CAPTIVE LABOR FORCE
OF THE AMERICAN GOVERNMENT
IN THE ENTIRE HISTORY
OF THE UNITED STATES.
- EVERY ASPECT
OF THE FUR INDUSTRY OPERATED
UNDER GOVERNMENT SUPERVISION,
AND WORKERS WERE GIVEN
ALLOTMENTS
THAT THEY USED
TO MAKE PURCHASES.
EVERY TRANSACTION WAS RECORDED
DOWN TO THE LAST PENNY.
SO FOR SOMEONE IN 1898
ON MARCH 26
TO PURCHASE TEA, SUGAR, MILK,
BUTTER, FLOUR, SOUP,
TOBACCO, MATCHES, FRUIT,
AND--I DON'T KNOW WHAT THAT IS--
HANDKERCHIEFS,
ONE PAIR OF BABY SHOES--
75 CENTS.
MOST PEOPLE DON'T EVEN KNOW
THAT THE UNITED STATES
HAD A FUR SEAL INDUSTRY,
MUCH LESS THE CONDITIONS
WITH WHICH THE WORKFORCE,
THE UNANGAN PEOPLE,
HAD TO LIVE WITH.
- ALASKA WAS PURCHASED
FOR $7.2 MILLION.
THE PRIBILOF ISLANDS ALONE
HAVE PROBABLY PAID
FOR THE STATE OF ALASKA
AT LEAST 10 TIMES OVER.
I KNOW IT'S MORE THAN THAT.
DID WE GET OUR FAIR SHARE? NO.
IF YOU GET PAID 25 CENTS A SKIN
WHEN THAT SKIN
IS WORTH HUNDREDS OF DOLLARS,
I DON'T THINK SO.
- WHAT'S IN HERE?
- THIS IS JUST
THEIR ORDER FORMS FOR SEARS.
- OK.
READING SOME OF THIS STUFF,
I HAVE TO STAND UP
AND JUST TAKE A DEEP BREATH
BECAUSE I WANT TO GET ANGRY.
THAT'S THE HARD PART.
HOW DO YOU HAVE A PIECE
OF HISTORY BE KNOWN AND BE TOLD
WITHOUT MAKING
THE NEXT GENERATION ANGRY?
- THIS IS PART OF HISTORY,
NO MATTER HOW IT MAKES YOU FEEL.
- YEAH.
HOW DO YOU HAVE IT GO FORWARD
INTO THE FUTURE
AND BE USED SO AS
NOT TO REPEAT ITSELF?
I THINK IT AFFIRMS THE NEED
FOR THIS HISTORY TO BE KNOWN.
IT'S NOT JUST OUR HISTORY.
IT'S THE HISTORY OF THIS NATION.
BOTH MY FATHER AND MY MOTHER
WERE BORN
ON SAINT GEORGE ISLAND.
MY FATHER, MICHAEL LESTENKOF,
WAS BORN IN 1913.
MY MOTHER STEFANIDA LEKANOF
WAS BORN IN 1919.
IN 1938, THEY GOT MARRIED.
LIKE ALL THE MEN
ON SAINT GEORGE ISLAND,
MY FATHER WORKED
IN THE FUR SEAL INDUSTRY.
THAT'S HIM TAKING
A CIGARETTE BREAK
IN FRONT OF THE SEAL PLANT.
- THAT'S IT. THAT'S IT.
A LITTLE MORE. A LITTLE MORE.
THAT'S IT. COME ON.
- ALL IN A DAY'S WORK, THE FIRST
SEAL HARVEST WOULD BEGIN
WITH AN EARLY-MORNING ROUNDUP
FROM THE BEACH.
PLACING THEMSELVES BETWEEN
THE SEALS AND THE SEA,
SHOUTING AND WHISTLING,
THEY DRIVE THE SEALS INLAND.
USING LONG HICKORY STICKS,
THEY DIVIDE OUT A POD
OF ABOUT 6 TO 12 SEALS.
- YEAH. A LITTLE MORE.
THAT'S IT.
- EACH SEAL IS DELIVERED
A SINGLE BLOW TO THE HEAD,
WHICH STUNS THEM...
AND WITH A KNIFE PIERCING
TO THE HEART, THEY ARE KILLED.
THE WASHHOUSE BUILDING
ON SAINT GEORGE ISLAND
IS THE ONLY REMAINING EVIDENCE
OF WHAT WAS ONCE
A VERY BUSY FUR SEAL INDUSTRY.
- ONCE THE FUR SEAL PROCESS...
- ANTHONY MERCULIEF
IS ONE OF THE LAST PEOPLE
ON SAINT GEORGE ISLAND TO HAVE
WORKED AT THE SEAL PLANT.
- THE DUMP TRUCKS WOULD BRING
THE PELTS TO THIS PLATFORM HERE.
THE WINDOWS WERE OPEN,
AND THE SEAL SKINS
WERE THROWN INSIDE THE TANKS
THAT ARE IN THERE
THAT ARE FILLED WITH SALTWATER.
- SO THIS WOULD BE
THE SKIN HOUSE OR THE WASHHOUSE?
- WASHHOUSE. YEAH.
THIS IS WHERE THE SKINS
WERE BROUGHT IN
THROUGH THE WINDOWS OVER THERE.
THIS WAS FILLED UP
WITH SALTWATER,
AND THE SKINS WERE PUT IN HERE
AND SOAKED OVERNIGHT.
- DO YOU KNOW HOW MANY SKINS
THEY WOULD BE ABLE TO FIT IN?
- IN EACH TANK,
PROBABLY 100 OR MORE.
THEY HAD AN OVERHEAD TROLLEY
THAT HUNG FROM
THIS TRACK RIGHT HERE.
THEY WOULD FILL THE THING
WITH SEAL SKINS
AND HAUL THEM DOWN
THROUGH THIS TRACK
TO THAT FAR END OF THE BUILDING,
WHERE THEY WERE PUT
ON THE TABLES
AND GIVEN TO THE BLUBBER PEOPLE
TO BLUBBER THEM.
- THEN FROM IN HERE
AND ON THESE TRACKS,
IS THIS HOW SKINS WERE BROUGHT
INTO THIS ROOM?
- RIGHT.
- AND THIS WAS
THE BLUBBERY SHOP, HUH?
- YEAH.
- AND WHAT ARE THESE TABLES FOR?
- THIS IS WHERE SKINS
WERE STACKED.
- SO HOPEFULLY,
YOU DIDN'T HAVE A BIG PILE.
- RIGHT, AND SMALL SKINS.
- YEAH. OH, OK, SIZE.
- THE EASY ONES.
THE BIG ONES WERE STRINGY
AND HARD TO BLUBBER.
- OH, OK.
SO YOU BLUBBERED HERE, TOO.
- YEAH.
- YEAH?
- YOU WOULD REACH OVER
AND GRAB A SKIN,
PUT IT ON THE BEAM
FUR SIDE UP,
AND YOU'D GRAB A KNIFE
FROM HERE,
CUT THE EARS OFF,
CUT A LITTLE BIT
OF THE SKIN
AROUND THE ARM HOLES.
THEN YOU TAKE THE SKIN
AND TURN IT AROUND
WITH THE BLUBBER SIDE UP
AND SCRAPE THE BLUBBER OFF.
THEN WHEN YOU GOT DONE
WITH THAT,
YOU FLIP IT OVER
AND DO THE OTHER SIDE.
- IN 2000, I CAME OVER WITH
MY DAD INTO THE SEAL PLANT HERE,
AND WHEN HE COUNTED DOWN,
HE SAID,
"THIS IS BLUBBER BEAM
NUMBER 13,"
AND HE SAID, "NO ONE WANTED
TO BLUBBER HERE
"BECAUSE 13
WAS AN UNLUCKY NUMBER,
"BUT SINCE I WAS BORN
ON OCTOBER 13, 1913,
IT'S MY LUCKY NUMBER, SO THIS
IS WHERE I BLUBBERED PELTS."
HE'D SAY, "I WAS BORN
ON THE 13th HOUR, TOO,"
BUT I DON'T THINK HE WAS.
HE JUST THREW THAT IN
FOR THE STORY.
[BOTH LAUGH]
IN 1941, THERE WERE
ABOUT 500 UNANGAN
LIVING ON SAINT GEORGE
AND SAINT PAUL ISLANDS,
BUT ONE YEAR LATER,
THERE WOULD BE NONE.
WORLD WAR II SHATTERED LIFE
ON THE PRIBILOF ISLANDS.
- WE USED TO HEAR THE PLANES
GOING OVER THE ISLAND.
THE BLACKOUTS STARTED RIGHT
AFTER PEARL HARBOR WAS BOMBED.
- MY MOTHER-IN-LAW
MARY BOURDUKOFSKY
WAS A YOUNG WOMAN
WITH YOUNG CHILDREN
WHEN WORLD WAR II BROKE OUT.
SAME RIGHT HERE.
- MM-HMM.
ALL THE WINDOWS AT NIGHT,
YOU HAMMER A BLANKET
TO MAKE IT DARK, NO LIGHTS,
NO KIND OF A LIGHT,
AND YOU'RE NOT SUPPOSED
TO EVEN SMOKE CIGARETTE
OUTSIDE OR NOTHING.
- IN JUNE 1942, THE JAPANESE
BOMBED THE HARBOR AT UNALASKA.
THEY INVADED THE ISLANDS
OF ATTU AND KISKA...
AND THEY TOOK
AMERICAN CITIZENS CAPTIVE.
- JUNE 1942.
THE NEWS ABOUT DUTCH HARBOR
BEING BOMBED
AT 6 A.M. REACHED US YESTERDAY.
NEXT CAME NEWS OF ATTU.
THE WAR BECAME
TOO HORRIBLY REAL.
IT SEEMED SENSIBLE TO PREPARE,
SO THE FIRST AND ONLY
AIR RAID SHELTER
IS BEING ERECTED ON SAINT PAUL.
WE APPEALED TO
THE GOVERNMENT AGENT
TO TAKE SOME ACTION
FOR THE COMMUNITY'S SAFETY.
WE BEGGED HIM TO EVACUATE
THE WOMEN AND CHILDREN AT LEAST.
- THE UNITED STATES GOVERNMENT
ORDERED A COMPLETE EVACUATION
OF ALL UNANGAN FROM THE ALEUTIAN
AND PRIBILOF ISLANDS.
YOU DIDN'T KNOW BEFOREHAND...
- NO. WE DIDN'T KNOW.
- THAT YOU WERE BEING EVACUATED?
- WHEN DID YOU FIND OUT?
- IT WAS SUNDAY AFTERNOON,
AND THEY USED TO HAVE A BIG
BALL GAME GOING ON ON SUNDAYS.
THAT SUNDAY HAPPENED TO BE
A BEAUTIFUL DAY,
AND MY HUSBAND WAS A BALLPLAYER,
AND HE WENT OUT, BUT I WAS HOME.
I HAD A LITTLE,
3-MONTHS-OLD BABY
AND A TWO-YEAR-OLD LITTLE BOY.
SO I WAS WASHING DIAPERS
BY WASHBOARD, YOU KNOW?
I DIDN'T HAVE NO
WASHING MACHINE,
AND THE BIG TRANSPORT LANDED
OVER THERE IN EAST LANDING.
PEOPLE WERE JUST PUZZLED,
WHAT WAS GOING ON,
AND THEN MY HUSBAND CAME
RUNNING HOME TO TELL ME
THAT THEY'RE TAKING EVERYBODY.
SAID, "THEY TELL US TO TAKE JUST
WHAT YOU HAVE ON YOUR BACK
AND CHANGE OF CLOTHES.
THAT'S ALL,"
AND WE DIDN'T HAD NO SUITCASES
BECAUSE WE NEVER TRAVEL,
SO I START FILLING UP CLEAN
50-POUND FLOUR SACKS
I HAVE WITH MY CHILDREN CLOTHES,
AND A CARDBOARD BOX I HAVE,
I FILLED THAT ONE, TOO.
THEY WALKED ALL THE WAY
TO EAST LANDING HERE.
IT WAS SO SAD.
WOMEN WERE CRYING.
ELDERS WERE CRYING,
AND PEOPLE CARRY A SACK
OF THEIR CLOTHES.
- EVERYONE WAS EVACUATED--
MARY'S FAMILY,
MY FATHER AND MY MOTHER,
MY OLDER SISTER AND BROTHER.
THEY WERE ALL TAKEN TO A CAMP
IN SOUTHEASTERN ALASKA,
TO A PLACE CALLED FUNTER BAY.
- THE HUNGER AND THE COLD,
THAT REALLY GETS US
IN FUNTER BAY.
I HAD TO DRESS MY LITTLE KIDS
WITH WHATEVER THEY HAD.
ALL THEIR THINGS GOT WORN OUT.
THEY GOT SMALL.
MY LITTLE BOY HAD NO SHOES,
AND IT'S BARE FLOOR,
AND THE MEMORIES
COME BACK TO ME.
- MM-HMM.
- YEAH.
WHAT THEY ISSUE US IS POWDERED--
POWDERED EGGS, POWDERED MILK.
WE HAD NO STOVE TO COOK, ANYWAY.
THERE WAS NO RUNNING WATER,
NO BATHS, NO TOILETS,
EXCEPT FOR ONE OVER THE BAY.
YOU HAVE TO WALK ON A PLANK.
- THERE WAS JUST THE HOLE.
- YEAH. THE WASTE JUST GOES
IN THE BAY...
AND THERE WERE FISH SWIMMING
AROUND, AND WE COULDN'T EAT IT.
HOW COULD WE?
AND THE BABIES WERE SICKLY--
COLD, SORES, IMPETIGOS...
AND WE WERE INFESTED WITH LICE.
ALL THAT 2 1/2 YEARS,
WE WERE THERE
CLEANING OUR HEADS
EVERY NIGHT SOMETIMES.
I ALWAYS SAY, "I HOPE
IT NEVER HAPPENS AGAIN."
- YEAH.
- TOGETHER, WE TRY TO
REMEMBER WHAT OUR PARENTS
AND GRANDPARENTS WENT
THROUGH DURING THE WAR.
SUFFERING THAT DIDN'T END
WHEN PEOPLE CAME BACK FROM
FUNTER BAY.
OUR PARENTS AND OUR
GRANDPARENTS CAME HOME TO FIND
THEIR HOUSES RANSACKED.
[PRIEST RECITING SCRIPTURE]
AMERICAN SOLDIERS HAD
TAKEN EVERYTHING OF VALUE,
EVEN ICONS FROM OUR CHURCHES.
BUT THE DEEPEST LOSS WAS OF
THOSE WHO NEVER RETURNED.
BECAUSE THEY DIED
AT FUNTER BAY.
IN 1960, I WAS BORN
ON SAINT GEORGE ISLAND,
THE 8TH OF 9 CHILDREN.
AND WHEN I WAS 3 YEARS OLD,
MY DAD FOLLOWED IN MY GREAT
GRANDFATHER INNOKENTY'S
FOOTSTEPS, AND HE BECAME
AN ORTHODOX PRIEST.
IN 1964, MY FATHER WAS
TRANSFERRED TO SERVE THE
PARISH OF SAINT PAUL ISLAND,
SO WE MOVED THERE.
[YELLING, METALLIC CLANGING]
THE 1970's WOULD LEAD
TO DIFFICULT TIMES
FOR THE COMMERCIAL
FUR SEAL INDUSTRY.
- WITH MAN'S DOMINION
OVER ANIMALS--AS GOD KNOWS,
THAT BIBLE IS
QUOTED TO US ENOUGH--
WITH THAT GOES RESPONSIBILITY.
- ON JANUARY, 1970, PRESIDENT
NIXON PROMISED PEACE WITH
NATURE, AND I QUOTE
THAT "PEACE WITH NATURE."
AND WHAT BETTER PLACE TO
START THAN TO END THE MASSACRE
OF SEALS BY
GOVERNMENT EMPLOYEES?
- IT'S FOR NOTHING EXCEPT
A LUXURY PRODUCT.
IT'S STRICTLY TO PLEASE THE
VANITY OF SOME WOMEN THAT
THESE SEALS ARE BEING CLUBBED
AND BLED AND STUCK AND SKINNED.
- WE ARE OPPOSED TO THE
UNNECESSARY KILLING OF ANY
ANIMAL, AND I THINK IT'S OUR
RESPONSIBILITY TO TAKE A COLD,
HARD LOOK AT WHAT WE'RE DOING.
- IT WAS AN INDISCRIMINATE
OUTRAGE, I THINK, THAT WAS
FOCUSED PRIMARILY
ON OUR PEOPLE.
WE WERE GETTING HATE MAIL FROM
ALL OVER THE WORLD FROM PEOPLE
WHO WERE BEING MISLED BY
CERTAIN KINDS OF ANIMAL RIGHTS
GROUPS FIGHTING AGAINST THE
TAKING OF FUR SEALS FOR THEIR
PELTS BY THE U.S. GOVERNMENT.
- TIME AND TIME AGAIN, WE'VE
BEEN THE ONES TO HAVE TO STAND
UP TO IGNORANCE ABOUT
THE FUR SEALS.
THE RUSSIANS AND THE AMERICANS
WANTED TO TAKE ALL THE FUR
SEALS FOR A QUICK PROFIT.
WE HAD BEEN THE ONES TO SAY THE
HARVEST HAD TO BE SUSTAINABLE.
NOW, OUTSIDERS
HAD A NEW DEMAND--
STOP THE HARVEST ALTOGETHER.
- WE HAD NO PLANS FOR AN
ALTERNATIVE ECONOMIC BASE,
SO UNCERTAINTY WAS
THERE, DEPRESSION SET
IN ON A COMMUNITY-WIDE BASIS,
AND WE BEGAN TO HAVE ONE
SERIES OF TRAGIC
EVENTS AFTER ANOTHER.
BETWEEN 1982 AND 1983, WE
HAD 100 DOCUMENTED SUICIDE
ATTEMPTS, 4 SUICIDES, 3 MURDERS.
DEFINITELY, WE SAW THE EFFECTS
OF A GOVERNMENT-RUN COMPANY
TOWN WHEN THE GOVERNMENT
DECIDES TO PULL OUT.
WE WERE LITERALLY
PLANNING ONE-WAY TICKETS
FOR PEOPLE OFF THE ISLAND.
[MOTOR RUNS]
- IN 1983, WE SAW THE
END OF THE COMMERCIAL
FUR SEAL INDUSTRY.
SO YOU WOULD SUSPECT YOU
WOULD SEE THE NUMBER OF
FUR SEALS INCREASE.
EVERYBODY ASSUMES THE
POPULATION IS GOING UP.
SOMETHING IS HAPPENING.
THIS HISTORICALLY WAS
A FUR SEAL ROOKERY.
WHEN THE RUSSIAN FUR TRADERS
FIRST CAME HERE, THE ROCKY
AREAS ON TOLSTOY ROOKERY
WERE COMPLETELY COVERED
WITH FUR SEALS.
IT'S REALLY HARD TO GIVE
PEOPLE AN IDEA WHAT A FEW
MILLION FUR SEALS
WOULD LOOK LIKE.
PEOPLE COME HERE NOW AND THEY
IMAGINE THAT THERE ARE A LOT
OF FUR SEALS.
YES, BUT NOT WHAT
THEY USED TO BE.
MY HUSBAND, PHIL ZAVADIL,
MOVED TO SAINT PAUL ISLAND
IN 1998 TO WORK WITH THE
TRIBAL GOVERNMENT OF SAINT PAUL
ON STARTING UP A NEW ECO
SYSTEM CONSERVATION OFFICE.
- WHEN I FIRST GOT HERE,
THERE WAS PROBABLY 1.2 MILLION
FUR SEALS ON THE PRIBS.
HERE WE ARE, 10 YEARS LATER,
AND YOU KNOW, I THINK THEY'RE
UNDER 600,000 FUR SEALS NOW.
UNLESS WE DO SOMETHING
DIFFERENT, I DON'T SEE
ANYTHING GETTING ANY BETTER.
- THE UNITED STATES
GOVERNMENT REMAINS RESPONSIBLE
FOR THE WELFARE OF THE FUR
SEALS UNDER THE MARINE MAMMAL
PROTECTION ACT.
THE TRIBAL GOVERNMENTS ARE
WORKING WITH THE NATIONAL
MARINE FISHERY SERVICE TO
CO-MANAGE THE FUR SEAL HERD
ON THE PRIBILOF ISLANDS.
- THE NORTHERN FUR SEALS
ARE FACING A LOT OF THE SAME
THREATS THAT MARINE MAMMALS
THROUGHOUT THE BERING SEA FACE.
THERE'S THE POTENTIAL
OF COMPETITION FOR PREY
WITH COMMERCIAL FISHERIES.
THE PRIMARY PREY FOR FUR
SEALS ON THE PRIBILOFS
IS WALLEYE POLLOCK.
IT'S ALSO THE LARGEST
FISHERY IN ALASKA.
THERE'S PREDATION.
KILLER WHALES TAKE
NORTHERN FUR SEALS ALL
AROUND THE PRIBILOF ISLANDS.
THERE'S DISEASE.
DISEASE HAS ALWAYS BEEN
PRESENT IN ANIMAL POPULATIONS,
BUT COULD INCREASE.
IT COULD BE BROUGHT IN BY AN
OUTSIDE SOURCE, OR SOMETHING
ELSE COULD TRIGGER
AN EPIDEMIC OF SORTS.
THERE'S ALSO ENTANGLEMENTS.
PACKING BANDS, TRAWL NET,
MONOFILAMENT.
ALL THESE THINGS THAT CAN COME
OFF OF FISHING BOATS OR OTHER
BOATS THAT FUR SEALS
CAN BECOME ENTANGLED IN.
AND THEN THERE'S
CLIMATE CHANGE.
AS WE SEE A WARMING OF
TEMPERATURES AND RECEDING
OF THE ICE PACK IN THE BERING
SEA, IT COULD CERTAINLY AFFECT
FUR SEAL BEHAVIOR, AS WELL AS
THE AVAILABILITY OF PREY.
SO COLLECTIVELY, ALL OF THOSE
THREATS TOGETHER MOST LIKELY
HAVE SOME SORT OF INFLUENCE.
AND WE'RE JUST TRYING TO TEASE
OUT WHICH ONE, OR MAYBE SOME
OTHER MIGHT BE
AFFECTING THE DECLINE.
- WE NEED TO DO SOMETHING.
THERE'S NOT GOING TO BE ONE
SIMPLE ANSWER, AND IT'S NOT
GOING TO HAPPEN OVERNIGHT.
I MEAN, IT'S TAKEN
US A COUPLE HUNDRED
YEARS TO GET HERE, AND THAT'S
PROBABLY HOW LONG IT'S GOING
TO TAKE TO GET THINGS
BACK ON TRACK.
I FEEL HOPEFUL, AND EQUALLY,
I FEEL UNCERTAIN.
[WOMAN SPEAKING UNANGAM
TUNUU LANGUAGE]
- KLUUCHIN.
- HOPEFULNESS AND UNCERTAINTY
ARE THE FEELINGS THAT WE HAVE
ABOUT OTHER ASPECTS
OF OUR CULTURE.
THERE ARE 6,000 DIFFERENT
LANGUAGES SPOKEN TODAY
AROUND THE WORLD.
CLOSE TO HALF OF THEM ARE ON
THE VERGE OF DISAPPEARING.
- SAAGLAX.
[SINGING]
- WHEN YOU LOSE A LANGUAGE,
YOU LOSE A WAY OF THINKING,
A WAY OF SOLVING PROBLEMS.
IT'S A LOSS.
IT'S A LOSS THAT
HURTS ALL OF US.
THERE ARE FEWER THAN 200
PEOPLE LEFT WHO GREW UP
SPEAKING UNANGAM TUNUU.
MARY IS ONE OF THEM.
HOPEFULLY, MY NEPHEW
WILL BECOME ANOTHER.
- I WANT TO GET TRADITIONAL
TATTOOS LIKE MY MOM'S.
THE LITTLE BLUE MOONS AND
THE DOT ON THE OTHER SIDE
OF THE CRESCENT IS TO
REPRESENT THAT THE MOON
IS ALWAYS WHOLE, EVEN WHEN
IT DOESN'T APPEAR TO BE.
- ALONG WITH MY DAUGHTER,
KATIA, MY SISTER, STEPHANIE,
AND OTHERS IN THE COMMUNITY,
WE'VE INITIATED A TRADITIONAL
DANCE GROUP.
- FOR OUR DANCE, WHENEVER
WE PERFORM--I WANT
THIS ONE RIGHT HERE.
-THE SEAL HEAD?
- MM-HMM.
- IT WILL FACE THE--
- FACE IN?
- MM-HMM.
- THIS ONE?
- YOURS DO THAT, TOO?
- DO THEY?
- YEAH, THEY DO.
- YOU THOUGHT THEY
WERE FRECKLES, HUH?
[LAUGHTER]
- YOU SAID IT WOULD GO THE
OPPOSITE WAY, THE OTHER
WAY, RIGHT? ON THE OTHER CHEEK.
- NO, THE SEALS--
OH, YEAH. THE OPPOSITE.
IT'S LIKE A MIRROR IMAGE.
I LIKE IT WHEN MY MOM
COMES TO ANCHORAGE.
I LIKE TO WALK BEHIND HER
IN PUBLIC PLACES AND WATCH
PEOPLE'S REACTIONS
AS WE'RE WALKING BY.
- OH.
- SHE GETS A LOT
OF DOUBLE TAKES?
- MM-HMM.
WHEN I FIRST DREW THEM, I WANTED
TO GET THEM PERMANENTLY DONE.
I WANTED TO JUST DO IT.
JUST DELVE RIGHT INTO IT.
- AND WHEN I DID MY FACE,
I WANTED TO DO IT 12 YEARS
EARLIER THAN I ACTUALLY DID
IT, BUT MAYBE THE TIMING
WOULDN'T HAVE BEEN RIGHT THEN,
ANYWAY, BECAUSE I STILL HAD
SOME THINGS THAT I
NEEDED TO EXPERIENCE.
AND SO, IT'S
ALL ABOUT TIMING.
THAT'S WHY I SAID YOU WILL
KNOW--WHEN THE TIMING IS
RIGHT, YOU'LL KNOW.
- OF COURSE, EVERYONE'S
GOING TO BE CURIOUS.
YOU KNOW, LIKE, I'VE
SEEN PEOPLE ASK YOU,
"ARE THOSE PERMANENT?"
OR "ARE THOSE REAL?"
AND THOSE ARE GOOD QUESTIONS,
BUT THE BETTER QUESTIONS ARE,
"WHAT DOES IT REPRESENT?"
"WHAT MADE YOU DO IT?"
"WHY DID YOU DO IT?"
TIMES HAVE CHANGED.
TIMES ARE CHANGING.
TIMES WILL ALWAYS BE CHANGING.
AND THIS IS MY CHOICE THEN TO
REPRESENT WHO I AM AND WHERE I
COME FROM, WHETHER OR
WHETHER NOT PEOPLE LIKE IT.
- IF AND WHEN YOU DO,
IF SOMEONE SAYS TO YOU,
"ARE THOSE PERMANENT?,"
WHAT ARE YOU GOING TO SAY?
- I DON'T KNOW.
I LIKE YOUR RESPONSE--
"ONLY AS PERMANENT AS I AM."
- YEAH.
YOU DIDN'T LOOK AT THEM YET.
- I WANT TO SEE.
[DRUM BEATING/SINGING]
- IF MY CULTURAL BASIS IS
BASED ON A RELATIONSHIP TO
SEALS AND SEA LIONS AND BIRDS,
WHEN THOSE ANIMALS ARE GONE,
WE'RE GONE.
THE ALEUT CULTURE
WILL NOT EXIST.
THE HOPEFUL THING IS THAT WE
ARE RAISING YOUNG GENERATION
PEOPLE WHO ARE REALLY
WANTING TO HAVE THAT BACK.
- HOW CAN WE REALLY
SUSTAIN THE ISLAND?
BUT IT'S REALLY UP TO THE
PEOPLE OF THE ISLAND TO MAKE
THAT DECISION FOR THEMSELVES.
- WHAT I WANT TO TELL
THE YOUNGER PEOPLE...
BE PROUD THAT YOU'RE AN ALEUT.
SOME PEOPLE CALL THOSE
ISLANDS OUT THERE ROCKS.
THEY'RE MORE THAN ROCKS.
THEY'RE OUR HOME.
[APPLAUSE]
[DRUM QUIETLY
BEATS STEADY PULSE]
- AS I WEAVE THIS ALEUT BASKET,
I'M USING MODERN MATERIAL.
IT'S ACTUALLY TELEPHONE WIRE.
BUT I'M USING A TECHNIQUE
THAT IS MOST LIKELY THOUSANDS
OF YEARS OLD.
AND AS I LOOK BACK
AT OUR HISTORY,
THAT'S WHAT IT'S ALL ABOUT.
WEAVING TIMES AND
PLACES TOGETHER.
I THINK ABOUT THE LAYER UPON
LAYER OF PEOPLE'S PASSAGES
HERE ON THE ISLAND...
THROUGH DIFFERENT ERAS
FOR THOUSANDS OF YEARS.
AND THE NEXT BASKET WE WEAVE...
WELL, IT'S GOING TO HAVE A BIT
OF EACH ONE OF
THOSE INTERACTIONS.
I DON'T EVER COMPLETE A BASKET
WITHOUT HAVING FIRST STARTED
ANOTHER ONE.
ALL OF MY BASKETS ARE
REALLY ONE BASKET INTERLACED
AND WOVEN TOGETHER.
YOU DON'T KNOW WHAT THE RESULT
IS GOING TO BE, BUT YOU JUST
KEEP WEAVING.
YOU JUST KEEP THINGS GOING
THROUGH TIME FOR COMING
GENERATIONS THAT
WE DON'T SEE YET.
[DRUM BEATS 3 TIMES]
[SINGING IN
UNANGAM TUNUU]
- OVER HERE, YOU
THINK IT'S FLAT?
- YEAH, YOU AND I
MIGHT TUMBLE DOWN.
[LAUGHTER]