all three species of North American
bears a found here
grounders black bears and polar bears
my name is Chris Morgan
have dedicated half my life to the study
in conservation of bass
now was embarked upon a three
thousand-mile journey
into the heart the Bears world
with me my good friend and filmmaker Joe
Pontecorvo
you don't notice it call for you look at
your crowd he crossed over everything
together
our goal is to peel back the layers a
myth
and misunderstanding on this complex
creature CI clown
put it in a place that to better
understand their personalities
all of them out the window
to witness first-hand how they live
today
and what the future might hold for the
Bears
the last frontier in
the
my journey has taken me through the
season as the brown bear
and black bear
from an area nearly untouched by man
to the most the urban environment in
alaska now
but the very edge of the North American
continent a new adventure is about to
unfold
I leave behind the cold metal and steel
prudhoe bay
and head to the home the polar bear
a plane touches down on a four mile long
windswept strip of land
known as barter island on the edge the
Beaufort Sea
fewer than 300 residents
mostly in Nubia eskimo call this remote
ireland home
but they are not alone
to share this frigid coast line with
another
great hunter the polar bear
while the rest to the Bears have to end
up for winter
polar bears sensed a change in season
and are anxious for the chill to set in
I'll
harbors a ice loving creatures 0
from an early age they are drawn to it 0
investigating any new formations on the
wart
what's fascinating to me about these
polar bears is that this own finely
tuned in adapted to life on
ice little better come right down the
street
here and broken through you look at 4.3
broken through this I see in fact the I
just got the form already
so there for ever testing the ice
conditions to see whose firm enough for
them to head out onto
and is not yet obviously
as adults they depend upon ice to hunt
unlike brown bears
polar bears a highly specialized
carnivals and hunt
almost exclusively one animal seals
the ring seal looks nervously around
exposed on this open expanse
the without firm in a vise
this bear has little chance to hunt down
the seal
it's late October and my now the ocean
should be frozen over
but this year winter has come late part
to the Laguna covered with ice
but the ocean
has yet to be tamed for now the Bears
trapped on land unable to hunt Mon
locals call this area the Polar Bear
campground
it's a nursery of sorts a safe haven for
mothers and young
this time of year
when other polar bears are waiting to
see ice 24 pregnant females are waiting
for enough snow to take their maternity
dans
this whole area in fact is really
important denning
females when they're pregnant they come
give birth in the habitat along this
coast here
in the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge
so many other females return to the same
area
to raise their cubs
they seem to have this recognition when
it comes to playing
female playing in one car was playing
with another come from its
its quite the interesting scenario
that's going on
at making a beeline right for thanks I
we've only been here a few minutes
an already we've attracted some
attention
I'm directly off when from he got a nose
in the average income twice and
she's coming this way we prolly won't
have a very long before we have to
make a hasty retreat you know the most
predatory in the bathroom
there is capable of great speeches
grizzly bears are you know they can run
35 miles an hour
so
there
think it's time to get in the pope she's
moving away with some determination we
need to make a retreat if you wanna jump
on Joe
guy looks like he's getting a really I
did take the chicken salad she can't
access
can't figure out for a meal of as how
they live their lives
they are curious creditors
everything about is about surviving the
cold
and hunting seals being a specialist is
two key to surviving the Arctic
it is true for the Bears as it is for
the Nubia eskimos
centuries these two hundred if the
article made their living
from the ocean the lives connected by
the animals they hunted
twice a year in spring and fall the new
PR eskimos hunt
bowhead whales
discarded remains a left on this bone
pile
in
seven o'clock in the morning with were
only
outskirts of town and is a good spot to
wait for bass right here
because ever seem to like coming out
under the cover of darkness
sometimes a case and wait in line around
a long time for
so what we're doing right now see if any
show up in his crossed
this guy's some close as we wanna get to
wale Meek
with this high fat content may help some
bears get through these tough times
when there's little else to eat if
warming trends continue
competition for this small pile of food
could get fierce
well for species already on the brink
polar bears will have some tough times
ahead
overnight snow flurry leaves fresh trips
for this young arctic fox to play in
up the icy lagoon is
to love activity the Bears use this new
platform to practice their light as a
feather walk
sea ice unlike fresh water rice
is flexible which gives the bears a lot
to experiment with
the fibers Bailey Wales used to filter
their food
has become the perfect choice for these
young cubs
play attracts attention and quickly
their mom claims the large Bailey
to strip out what he can from it I'm
with the bone pile nearly exhausted his
mother frantically dicks was scrapped
buried in the snow
but her fine soon draws attention from
another family
ok
tensions are high
as bears on cover every last bit of
whalebone
scraping want me to count from the bones
a find like this is worth protecting
and his mother bear is not about to give
up a meal so easily
them
more
this young man I will have to seek out
his own meal
fortunately for him the weather appears
to be getting worse
temperatures have dipped to a
bone-chilling twenty degrees below
Greece ice
starting to cover the water
and winds batter the tiny island
the town is battening down the hatches
as the storm sets in
I'm on
ones ice begins to form the ocean
freezes over in just a few days
winter has finally taken hold I'm
the town now in its final days of
sunlight
bids farewell to the Bears as they head
out
onto the pack ice to hunt I
the Sun will vanish below the horizon
I'm and not reappear for another two
months
I'm
for now the world is in darkness
miles out on the pack ice polar bears a
hunting seals
stalking their prey I'm in the inky
blackness have winter
on
near the end of January the Sun begins
to reappear
on
it's a time of transition
with more light each day
and by many in mid-spring the Sun is up
24 hours a day
and it's safe enough for us to venture
out onto the pack ice
when the eight miles out on a thin shell
for voice
searching for polar bears
but I'd be foolish to attempt this alone
of
it
Dale brower grew up on the North Slope
maybe we'll
get on a high point look around meaning
he grew up in the world completely alien
to most diverse
0 he's a really fresh
is that actually on top us LEC tracks
from a five hours ago
maybe 14 hours ago solely they weren't
here then
that's for sure he might have heard the
snow we see the in in
kinda snuck back often new this these
pressure ridges hear him he could just
be hiding out with
up
in this feature was white landscape it's
the best to have the advantage
problem is if they're off in the
distance of the behind the ice to easily
obscured even a large animal like a
polar bear
is this a weather from
coming in here yes actually the water
skied us
their water from the openly reflecting
in the sky a
so if you headed to to all those clouds
you find open water open water area
under me and has a good chance as for
the polar bears that were tracking here
it's been an exhaustive search and still
the bear remains elusive
when we check in which way the wind is
blowing
just so that entryway is on the opposite
end
we own it facing the wind
room because that's really important
when it blows for your fifty miles an
hour up
the morning snow cluttering our camp is
modest
the functional in every way up
I'm discovering there's little that dale
does that doesn't relate directly to our
own survival
up even the caribou hides seem to be the
perfect
insulation against the cold CR
fits in the by giving cell phone up
why
polisher that's my polar bear
it's the best for out there is a fist
for keeping the window
oh yeah its keeps the window and then it
does Andrew
it doesn't frost so does that collects
snow and stuff
interested in in it stays pretty clean
even know you you get it dirty you can
just ripen in the snow in the here with
this clean itself
basically like a polar bear after its
done with skill
this Robin the snow take us know about
the
just take longer stirred up for
polar bears a stealth hunters and just
because you don't see them
doesn't mean they're not there see what
we can do
outbreak calls perfect vantage point as
or send the perfect vantage point
looking for polar bears
all camps right here it is easy to
forget this
Mac bank right in the middle polar bear
habitat
all the way to the horizon all I can see
is
ice giant jagged peaks and troughs
devices far as you can see
and is a barren hardstyle landscape
she can read the ice here well you not
going to survive
polar bears a master's
reading the ice good patrolling the edge
elite
smiling for any trace of a seal
well
well but sneaking up on the ceiling
open water is a challenge even for a
polar bear
well
the best chance for me list sniff out
the seals breathing hole
or even a den with seal pups it
it's a rare sight but dale has observed
polar bears hunting
like the there was a whole here Cheryl
see if the whole is here
he could now ok well the whole check
this site out where the field
hill this basile out it's one of the
earliest instinctive behaviors for polar
bear cubs
up while their mom rests
up these cultural practice what it takes
to become the apex predator the Arctic
up learning to lead with your nose up
investigate anything out of the ordinary
leap across
unstable chunks a vice and of course
the belly flop but when Mom homes
the Cubs know it's time to continue with
the real heart
polar bear tracks have led us here a
whaling cam
pushed to the edge in the lead a bear
was spotted just a day ago
perhaps the very one we're looking for
to the new Pia whale hunting isn't
ancient way of life
continues nearly unchanged today good
with 24 hours have lighted the rhythm of
life is set by the whales
not the Sun
the
I'm
further
whale hunting is by far the most
dangerous part of their subsistence life
these young people doing it just the way
that their ancestors did
he's constantly to any 22 years old
the beach gonna roll and its importance
to the community is vital
your when you become a captain in its
your first will you give the poor thing
way to all the whaling crews
you just learned over time that what you
kids
is really yours as a hunter you're here
too he peed
the town in the family's not really for
your so
the new PS commitment to this tradition
has helped keep his party the coastline
3 I've
oil development in without their
protection
this vital habitat may disappear
completely
while
in the background blowhole maybe I'll
wait is over
as the whale approaches
to camp becomes dead silent what
way as soon as the whale surfaces
two bogeys launched is a tense moment as
the men Patil towards the massive whale
somewhere just under the surface
happening while by hand is extremely
dangerous
bowhead whales can weigh sixty tons
one swipe up its enormous tail fluke
could easily crushed a tiny craft
up
because colonels with the clinic at the
whaler to the water
two holes through the ice to go right
through
block and tackle a little bit whole
whaling
you
world
this bowhead whale will feed several
families throughout the season
and perhaps the polar bears as well
it's a cycle of life has remained
unchanged for thousands of years
the
other whales will continue their annual
migration
following the open leads East to this
summer grounds
in the Beaufort Sea
to the ice is too thin for us to go any
further
it's late May and the pack ice is slowly
retreating
right now
it certainly feels treacherous out here
there are no shortcuts in the Arctic
you have to know when to call it quits
is Dale often says
if you don't come back this season you
can't hunt next season
it's a good lesson
even for a polar bear up
but continually having to haul himself
onto the ice takes an immense amount of
energy
polar bears face this challenge every
spring
for the impacts have a warming world
made matters worse
losses pack ice is estimated at 11
percent per decade
the Bears fragile hunting platform is
getting fed
in this mother and cover found
themselves
in ocean
melting ice
and if warming trends continued seems
like this
will become common
like many animals that have made such
great leaps in their revolution to
survive
the world may be changing too fast for
polar bears to keep up with
while the endless Arctic zones slowly
erodes the ice
the brings renewed life to the tundra
and the season the grisly is only just
begun
I'll
it's the perfect time to head south and
into the heart of the Brooks Range
I
he sparred
were following the trails have great
migrations from seasons past
house trails right on the mountains
right now runs filing tax
and we're hoping these caribou tracks
will point the way to Arctic Grizzlies
maybe our best chance at a closer look
at this elusive predator
but finding nearly half a million
caribou in the fastness have the western
Arctic
takes patience and persistence which pic
2 spot because his caribou trails for
around down I the valley
each side of the 10 here no single
carrier
and no single bear book hopefully when
the Carrboro for security in big numbers
and as my right as well that's what
we're hoping for
within list to the aid of aerial
cameramen Daniels at
to help document the herd and hopefully
the Bears if we find them
so based on what Jim from fishing game
said he said that
the females in caps are running along
this line here to the north okay and
this is also where he expects will see
the Bears but it's really
unpredictable it's completely unprepared
caribou
you never know where they're going to go
on caribou are the ultimate Wanderers
within a single year the western Arctic
heard all range across the quarter
at alaska an area the size of Montana
on def
make money
many of
unique
looks like we're in luck
we've just caught the tail end of a
massive heard
go well
we've just settle down a spot here
some trying to stay very quiet which you
saw so the weather on the horizon
because they're just so ever vigilant
uniform all Sanders the best
that's when the safety in numbers comes
from if you're eating you not watching
watching not eating so if you're in a
group you can do both
spring is carving season
a sore these newborns are just a few
days old
caribou cars can run with him hours are
being born
it's a matter of survival
newly born come home so most vulnerable
to predators
and they have to stay close to mama all
times
rules
I'm never far behind
this gray wolf is testing the herd
looking for any signs of weakness
he's joined by another from the pack
together they've cut the hood at home
but soon the herders regrouped
and the walls give up the chase
there's little rest for the home until
they complete their seasonal migration
to this summer range
carol was largely sustained by the
high-energy sugars found in Arctic
lichen
so prized is this plan
that many biologists believe the
availability of lichen
during the winter months can profoundly
impact caribou numbers
well caribou this landscape would look
the way it does aerate the soil says
they're walking to make it more
productive plants
even their hair provides nesting
material for migratory birds around here
you can imagine how much fertilizer
half-a-million camera to create
like blood vessels
flowing across this giant landscape
on
ok number three cups
the spring comes in the first year of
life foraging along the hillside
Arctic Grizzlies must make the most of
the short summers
and that includes is mating pair to
somehow found each other in this
vast expanse Grizzlies must cover
great distances just to find enough food
an Arctic grisly in open tundra can have
a home range the sizeof yellowstone
what you touch down
keeping up with the grisly is nearly
impossible
for the caribou their journey is nearly
over
the herd is finally made it to this
summer range the completion
have their journey but caribou a
wonderous
and they don't stay put for long
with the herd moving on and only
fleeting glimpses
Grizzlies we are left with few choices
an old report to the salmon run has
given us some hope
him back in
what but this far inland
it's a long shot even if we find someone
in the river
no 1 I've spoken with has actually seen
Arctic Grizzlies fishing
to caribou taunt me but it's not them on
looking for
your finding best time is the priority
here
British Grizzlies are around it's best
to be prepared
carry a shotgun only as an extreme
precautions
and believe it or not they really
popular thing we currently position
traditional route
the lovely stuff on surprises morsels
been left behind
actual my look at this place in think he
doesn't offer very much
for pieced together a diet little bit by
little bit they get by here
trucks or through here
look at this fresh grizzly bear tracks
I'm right in front of it caribou track
so both the species using this river to
get from A to B
and occasionally for bears lucky we have
to prey on the character especially
during
carving season
wow look at that the salmon a running
the question is
where the Bears
the time for a cuppa coffee I think
after hours of waiting there's a shadow
moving through the willows
own yeah right
as a third cup coming up the river cast
here
she's crossing here I do not want to
surprise his paddle
Arctic Grizzlies have a much more
aggressive reputations and coastal brown
bears
she seems pretty cool she seen us
just finding one would be chanson of
how far back as the third one right
behind the second
okay the fourth one is way back there in
the Willows
on this side of the creek but now
we suddenly surrounded by four
the family seems to be using the river
is a corridor
but their food
is buried in the tundra
hey serum group are an important source
of protein for Arctic Grizzlies
the Bears lack of interest in the salmon
is puzzling but the charm sermon don't
have nearly the fat and calories as does
the bears eat along the coast
once they leave the salt water to head
upstream
they stop eating all the energy goes
into reaching the spawning ground where
they were born
for these fish that's roughly 400 river
miles
it after weeks of swimming upstream
they've used a tremendous amount of
their reserves to get here
and the ones vibrant color has faded
from their skin
males will gather and fight for position
females arise good
West is courting process starts
it can take hours or even days to
complete
it
the family has returned
but this time they staked out a spot on
the river
mom is completely focused fishing
she's landed a huge
chum salmon
the whole family retreats into the
Willows to share the fish
here in the Arctic a catch like this is
quite a bounty
mom quickly returns to the river's edge
the Cubs will pick this fish clean
while mom looks for more
comes
all lined up waiting for mom to catch
dinner
she's quickly proving to be a skilled
Fisher and by the looks at these Cubs
she's been an excellent provided for the
first two and a half years of their
lives
it's hard it's hard to even imagine what
comes
they're almost as big as she is at best
a the Cubs have been watching her
closely
and now instead of feasting off what
she's cool they seem to be
interested in learning to fish
themselves
these new experiences show off how
different each of these comes I'll
they're all individuals this cop has
plenty of confidence
he's borderline troublesome one close
enough that's close enough
as close to North
okay it's alright UK
it's alright he ventures much further
than the other two
and seems to be quite bold this boldness
concerns his mom quite a bit
but it's also what heals him his first
catch
once created the lovable Panda
yeah
when he catches something it's his alone
he is already showing his independence
the other two cubs more plush and cub
liked in their brother
one is playful
anxious as the bounds into the water
after fish the other copies
much more cautious sticking close to mom
for the first time in the days we've
been watching her she's able to rest
comfortably on the shore
while the cops patrol the shallow River
it's doubtful they know this is their
last summer under her care and guidance
at last smallest colby is beginning to
focus on the salmon
mom follows close behind stirring up the
fish
she gives up the chase letting her come
finish to catch
are attacks
it's not uncommon to see a mother get
very protective and aggressive while
fishing
to me she seems intent on preparing
these cops for life on their own
as she does with finding food though for
your way here
after several days is being watched
her curiosity for ross has finally
peaked
a where you are a good mama all you are
so sweet
look at her backing up like that
we're gonna get out of your way
that's our cue
will take a cue from this a good lesson
for us to keep in mind is to always
leave on a good note
while it may be some time before they
come across people again
when they do we won their memory of us
to be a positive one
with a few short hops
she rounds up her family to call it a
day
really didn't know when we entered this
situation if she was going to be
accepting a bus or not and she's emerged
to be this wise
mature d for careful female
it's taken us time to get to know them
to understand that so that we know what
their limits on and it reminds you that
any two bears are as different as any
two people you might in Kent
and over this journey it's become clear
the world these bears inhabit is
fast getting must remain so
to sustain such great wonders
the resources we so prized are embedded
in the land that sustains all
life here
like the great plains of Africa
Alaska is the last stronghold for summer
the
us wildest creatures
I've never felt so comfortable also a
life is like to hear
this may be the end of my journey but
Alaska's wilderness
its wildest creatures
always call me back
to learn more about what you've seen on
this nature program
visit PBS Todor